So at this point we're going to talk about hyperparameters.
이 시점에서 hyperperameter에 관해 얘기할 거예요
And we're going to introduce three of them.
그중 세 가지를 소개할게요
So a reminder of what is a hyperparameter.
hyperperameter가 뭔지 다시 말씀드릴게요
We talked about it a bit last week.
지난주에 비트 얘기를 좀 했어요
A hyperparameter is one of these levers.
하이퍼파라미터는 이 레버 중 하나예요
That is something which you as the experimenter just gets to choose what you want it to be.
실험자로서 원하는 걸 선택할 수 있는 거예요
There's no particular hard and fast rule about what it should be, and you're meant to use a process
무엇이어야 하는지에 대한 어렵고 빠른 규칙은 없어요 hyperpaameter
known as hyperparameter optimization to try different values and see what works best for your task at
최적화라는 프로세스를 사용해야 합니다 다양한 값을 시도하고 당면한 작업에 뭐가 최선인지 알아보기 위해서요
And in reality, what what we are actually doing is basically trial and error.
사실 우리가 하는 일은 시행착오를 겪는 거예요
It's a bit of guesswork and then experimentation, because there aren't necessarily any theoretical
추측과 실험이 뒤따르는 작업이죠 비트를 한 방향으로만 설정해야
reasons why it should be set one way.
하는 이론적 이유가 없거든요
It's a matter of practical experiment.
실질적인 실험의 문제죠
And so often you find in these things when people have a something that's working well and there's a
이런 경우 종종 발견하게 되는데 잘 작동하는 프로그램일 경우 몇 가지 제어 매개
few, a few controlling parameters, but they're not quite sure how what they should be set to.
변수가 있지만 어떻게 설정해야 할지 잘 모르는 경우가 있죠
We don't yet have the theory to say what they should be.
어떤 형태가 돼야 할지 아직 이론적으로 몰라요
We just call it a hyperparameter.
hyperperameter라고 부르죠
That's what it's called.
그렇게 불러요
And it means that you're in this world of trial and error and guesswork until you pick the right settings.
올바른 설정을 고를 때까지 시행착오와 추측의 세계에 있다는 뜻이죠
That works best for your model.
모델에게 가장 잘 어울려요
I'm oversimplifying a bit, of course, but hopefully you get the general idea.
비트를 좀 단순화했지만 대충 이해하셨으면 좋겠네요 get it get it
So there's going to be three of them that are most critical.
가장 중요한 세 가지가 있어요
In the case of Q Laura fine tuning, and I want to introduce them to you now and then.
Q 로라 파인 튜닝의 경우 이따금 소개해 드릴게요
We will be playing with them in our time on this.
그들과 함께 작업할 거예요
The first of them is called R, which stands for rank.
첫 번째는 R이라고 해요 직위를 뜻하죠
And it means simply how many dimensions are we going to use for these lower rank matrices within within
라마 건축물에서 낮은 계층의 행렬을 만들 때 사용하는 차원이 얼마나
the Lama architecture, the the inner layers have dimensionality of like 1004 thousand dimensions.
되는지를 뜻합니다 내부 층의 차원은 100만 4천 차원에 달하죠
We're going to want much smaller number of dimensions in our lower rank matrices.
낮은 계급 행렬에서 훨씬 적은 수의 치수를 확보해 주세요
That's that's the whole idea of them.
그게 그들의 의도예요
Um, so typically, uh, as I said, there's no hard and fast rules different tasks look for different
아까 말했듯이 어렵고 빠른 규칙은 없어요 이런 언어 생성 모델에서
values of R to start with when you're working in this kind of language generation models.
작업할 땐 다양한 작업과 다양한 R 값을 찾죠
I think a good rule of thumb that I've, I've always used and that I see people use generally in the
제가 항상 써먹던 경험 법칙이 하나 있는데 일반적으로 사람들이 쓰는
community start with eight, which is a small number.
걸 보니 8부터 시작하는 것 같아요 작은 숫자죠
Um, and that means that it will use up very lower memory and it will run fairly fast.
아주 적은 메모리를 사용하고 꽤 빨리 실행된다는 뜻이죠
Um, and then double it to 16, which will take up more memory and run more slowly and see whether or
다음엔 16으로 두 배 늘리죠 메모리를 더 잡아먹고 더 천천히 실행하면서 더 나은 결과를
not you get better results and then potentially double again until you reach a point where you're getting
얻는지 보고 잠재적으로 또 두 배가 될 때까지요 결과물이 감소하는 지점까지 도달할
diminishing returns.
때까지요
It's slowing down and it's taking longer, but you're not seeing any improvement.
속도가 느려지고 시간이 더 오래 걸리는데 나아지는 게 보이지 않아요
And then, you know, there's no point in having a higher R, you've already got the power you need
높은 R을 갖는 건 의미가 없어요 이미 데이터를 위해 필요한 힘을
for the data that you've got.
갖고 있으니까요
So that's r uh, the next one that we'll talk about is alpha.
다음은 알파에 대해 얘기해 보죠
And Alpha is quite simply a scaling factor that is multiplied.
알파는 단순히 배율 요인이 두 배인 거예요
It's applied to these Laura A Laura B matrices.
로라 A. 로라 B 매트릭스에 적용했어요
And that is then used to change the weights in the model.
그 무게로 모델의 무게를 바꾸죠
The formula for what it's worth is that the amount that you change the weights in the model by in your
값어치의 공식은 목표 모듈에서 모델에서 무게 중심을 변경하는
in your target modules.
양이에요
Is alpha times the A matrix times the B matrix.
알파 곱하기 A 곱하기 B 곱하기예요
They get all multiplied together.
모두 함께 번성하죠 Get up, Get up
So bigger alpha means more effect.
알파가 클수록 효과도 크군요
And in practice the rule of thumb that is used I think almost ubiquitously I've I've always used it
실제로 사용되는 경험 법칙은∙∙∙ 거의 보편적으로 전 항상 사용했고 항상
and I've always seen it this way in examples is to set alpha to be double R.
이런 식으로 봤어요 예를 들어 알파를 R로 설정하는 거죠
So if you start with an R of eight your alpha is 16.
R이 8로 시작하면 알파는 16이 되죠
Then when you go up to an R of 16 alpha is 32 and then 32 would be 64.
16 알파 R은 32 32는 64가 되겠죠
So that is the good rule of thumb.
경험으로 터득한 좋은 법칙이죠
But of course it's always worth experimenting with different alphas to see if that if that changes the
물론 다양한 알파로 실험해볼 가치가 있죠 그게 여러분의 정확성을 바꿀지
your your accuracy.
보려면요
And then the third and final of our three essential hyperparameters is the actually saying, what will
세 번째이자 마지막 핵심 하이퍼파라미터는 아키텍처에 적용하는
be the target modules that you will focus on adapting in your architecture?
데 집중할 대상 모듈이 무엇인가 하는 거죠
Which which of these layers are you going to select to focus on uh, and uh, generally the most common
이 중 어떤 레이어에 초점을 맞출지 선택하세요 일반적으로 가장 일반적인 선택은
choice and the one that we'll be using is that you focus on the attention layers.
주의 집중 레이어에 초점을 맞추는 거죠
That's very common.
흔한 일이에요
You'll see that in the code that's going to make more sense when you see it.
코드에서 보실 수 있어요 보시면 더 이해가 될 거예요
Uh, there are situations when you want to to target other target modules.
다른 목표 모듈을 목표로 삼고 싶을 때가 있죠
Um, if for example, uh, you're generating something that, that where you want the output to be in
예를 들어, 여러분이 뭔가를 생성할 때 결과물이 완전히 다른 언어로
like a completely different language or something like that, then you might want to, uh, to target
나오길 원한다면 최종 레이어 일부를 대상으로 하는
some of those final layers.
게 좋을 거예요
So you'll see some, some, some that I'll give you more context in a moment about how that works.
그래서 여러분이 보실 건 그게 어떻게 작동하는지에 대한 좀 더 많은 컨텍스트를 알려드리죠
But generally speaking, the most common by far is to target the attention head layers.
하지만 일반적으로 가장 많이 사용되는 것은 주의 헤드 층이에요
That's what we will do.
그렇게 할 거예요
And you will see how that set up in a moment.
어떻게 설정됐는지 곧 보실 거예요
And with that, we are now going to head to Google Colab to look at this, to look at some models,
이제 구글 Colab으로 가서 몇 가지 모델을 살펴보고 로라에 관해 얘기해 보죠
to talk about Laura, to talk about Q, Laura and to see these three hyperparameters in action.
그리고 hyperperameter 3개가 어떻게 작동하는지 볼게요
Let's do it.
시작하죠